A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8 FA280
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
1953-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA280
5.72 Cubic Feet 13 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement note
This series is arranged in 2 subseries:
Subseries 1 Administrative Files
Subseries 2 Grant Files
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: administrative and grant files.
United States; War relief; Public welfare; Public health; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; Child psychology; Child welfare; Education, Rural; Mental health; Hygiene; Law; Legal issues; Legal research; Medical education; Medical research; Medicine, Rural; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Social Science Research Council; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Charles W.; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Yale University; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Harvard University; Columbia University
- Administrative Files, 1
  - Board Reports, February 1, 1955-February 1, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board Reports, May 22, 1956-November 10, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - News Releases, December 23, 1955-January 4, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Publicity, November 1955-May 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Grant Files, 2
  - Albany Medical College of Union University, November 1, 1955-March 28, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Albany Medical College of Union University, September 30, 1960-May 13, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Albany Medical College of Union University (Auxiliary Folder), January 1954-June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Boston University School of Medicine, November 4, 1955-November 18, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Carnegie Corporation - Behavioral Science and Medical Education, September 26, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, August 25, 1955-May 9, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, April 13, 1961-April 9, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Cornell University Medical College, May 9, 1955-July 8, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Duke University School of Medicine, November 17, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Emory University School of Medicine, May 9, 1955-June 28, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Emory University School of Medicine, October 31, 1955-May 13, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Emory University School of Medicine, October 2, 1956-February 11, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine, May 23, 1956-March 14, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine, April 2, 1957-September 27, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine, January 16, 1958-May 21, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine, July 27, 1958-December 26, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine, February 1, 1962-January 24, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine (Progress Report), January 1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Georgetown University School of Medicine (Progress Reports - Appendices), February 1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Harvard Medical School, April 1, 1955-November 9, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, June 1, 1953-March 31, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, April 2, 1954-December 12, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, January 16, 1956-December 28, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, January 7, 1957-December 31, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, January 6, 1958-December 31, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, January 5, 1959-August 19, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), January 1950 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), June 1955-March 1958 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - New York University College of Medicine, August 17, 1955-December 12, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - New York University College of Medicine, January 19, 1956-May 29, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - New York University College of Medicine, August 14, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - New York University College of Medicine, August 23, 1957-December 1, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Northwestern University Medical School, June 6, 1955-December 29, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Northwestern University Medical School, January 3, 1956-May 17, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Northwestern University Medical School, August 14, 1957-June 26, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Northwestern University Medical School, November 14, 1958-May 10, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, February 13, 1953-October 15, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, October 28, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, October 28-30, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, November 2, 1953-February 27, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, March 1, 1954-December 29, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, January 1, 1955-April 29, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, May 2, 1955-July 29, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, August 1, 1955-December 23, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, January 1, 1956-February 29, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, March 1, 1956-April 27, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, May 1-28, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, June 1, 1956-December 21, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, January 3, 1957-November 29, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, January 2, 1958-December 29, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, January 27-28, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, February 2, 1959-August 31, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, September 1-22, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine, October 2, 1959-February 18, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1954 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1954 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1956 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1956 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder - Shirley, Hale F.), March 2, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Stanford University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder - Shirley, Hale F.), March 2, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Tulane University School of Medicine, June 1, 1955-August 30, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Tulane University School of Medicine, September 11, 1956-January 7, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Tulane University School of Medicine, March 29, 1960-February 28, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Tulane University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Tulane University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1965 (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - University of Chicago Medical School - Biological Sciences, June 3, 1955-June 15, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - University of Chicago Medical School - Biological Sciences, October 26, 1956-June 29, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School, April 1, 1954-December 28, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 73)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School, January 16, 1956-August 30, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School, February 7, 1958-October 22, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School (Auxiliary Folder), December 1955 (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School (Auxiliary Folder), December 1955 (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School (Auxiliary Folder), January and December 1957 (Box 10, Folder 78)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School (Auxiliary Folder), June 1958 (Box 11, Folder 79)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School (Auxiliary Folder), June 1958 (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - University of Pennsylvania Medical School (Auxiliary Folder), June and October 1958 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, May 17, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, May 28, 1955-February 2, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 83)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, March 1, 1956-November 8, 1957 (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, March 13, 1958-March 4, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 85)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, March 17, 1960-July 9, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 86)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, October 29, 1962-May 21, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 87)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry, October 3, 1963-November 20, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry (Auxiliary Folder), December 1954 (Box 12, Folder 89)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry (Auxiliary Folder), October 1963-February 1964 (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - University of Rochester School of Medicine and Dentistry (Auxiliary Folder), March 1966-June 1967 (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine, July 15, 1955-December 22, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine, January 6, 1959-April 27, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 93)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine, May 1, 1959-May 16, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 94)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine, June 2, 1960-November 23, 1960 (Box 12, Folder 95)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine, January 12, 1961-May 27, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 96)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1957 (Box 13, Folder 97)
  - University of Southern California School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), 1959 (Box 13, Folder 98)
  - Vanderbilt University School of Medicine, November 17, 1955 (Box 13, Folder 99)
  - George Washington University School of Medicine, January 6, 1956-September 15, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 100)
  - George Washington University School of Medicine, August 27, 1959-February 21, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 101)
  - George Washington University School of Medicine (Auxiliary Folder), October 1947-November 1955 (Box 13, Folder 102)
  - Washington University School of Medicine (St. Louis), May 17, 1956 (Box 13, Folder 103)
  - Western Reserve University School of Medicine, June 30, 1954-June 25, 1958 (Box 13, Folder 104)
  - Yale University School of Medicine, May 10, 1955-November 20, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 105)